<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An humble vindication of a free admission unto the Lords-Supper published for the ease, support, and satisfaction of tender consciences (otherwise remediless) in our mixt congregations / as it was delivered at two sermons upon the occasion of this solemnity in the weekly labours of Iohn Humfrey ...</title>
            <author>Humfrey, John, 1621-1719.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1652</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 107 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 48 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A45133</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H3682</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R43272</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">27123622</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 27123622</idno>
            <idno type="VID">109976</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A45133)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 109976)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1721:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An humble vindication of a free admission unto the Lords-Supper published for the ease, support, and satisfaction of tender consciences (otherwise remediless) in our mixt congregations / as it was delivered at two sermons upon the occasion of this solemnity in the weekly labours of Iohn Humfrey ...</title>
                  <author>Humfrey, John, 1621-1719.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <editionStmt>
                  <edition>The second edition.</edition>
               </editionStmt>
               <extent>[6], 88 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for E. Blackmore ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1651.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Errata: p. [2].</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Close and open communion.</term>
               <term>Lord's Supper --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Rekeyed and resubmitted</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:109976:1"/>
            <p>An humble VINDICATION Of a Free ADMISSION Unto the <hi>Lords-Supper.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>PUBLISHED For the eaſe, ſupport, and ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of tender Conſciences (otherwiſe remedileſs) in our mixt Congregations.</p>
            <p>As it was delivered at two Sermons upon the occaſion of this ſolemnity, in the weekly labours of <hi>Iohn Humfrey,</hi> Maſter of Arts, and Miniſter of <hi>Froome</hi> in SOMERSETSHIRE.</p>
            <p>The Second Edition.</p>
            <q>
               <p>A Priest is taken from among men, and ordayned for men in things pertaining to God, who can reaſonably bear with the ignorant, and them that are out of the way, for that himſelf alſo is compaſſed with infirmity.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Heb. 5 1, 2.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>E. Blackmore,</hi> at the Angel in <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard, 1652.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:109976:2"/>
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>Page 9. line 6. for <hi>ſin,</hi> read in, page 24. line 26. read <hi>Let ſome of our other ſide.</hi> page 74. line 20. for <hi>most,</hi> read more.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:109976:2"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Courteous Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Aving (by good pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence) had ſome gleanings of this en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuing diſcourſe, as it was delivered by the worthy Author in own Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation, and conferring my notes with an honoured Christian, I found ſuch ſupport and contentment to my own conſcience in the ſympathy of his approbation, that made me very importunate to have them perfected;
<pb facs="tcp:109976:3"/>and having at length obtained a compleat copy, I could not but hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly think it an engagement, much conducing to the glory of God, to get this precious light, left under a bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhell in a private auditory, to be ſet up publikely in a candlestick of the Church, that the ſpirits of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny others might be thereby diſclouded from the like ſcruples, that moſt ſad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly hinder the bleſſed enjoyment of this Ordinance of Christ.</p>
            <p>The worke needs not the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation of another, having in it ſome exquiſite notions, and ſelf ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency enough, to commend it and its compiler; and although it must expect ſeverall cenſures (which is the common fate of the beſt works)
<pb facs="tcp:109976:3"/>according to the variety of mens hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours in theſe times, yet I am per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded by experience, to an impar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall and diſengaged judgment, pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſing it with a ſingle eye, it will afford aboundant comfort and ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction, it being weighty, ſpirituall, and ingenuous, and a piece wherein (if I may uſe the word of one more learnedly able to judge of it) Mr. <hi>Humfrey</hi> has comprized the moſt materiall things that can be ſaid in this buſineſs, as rationally and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſely as any beſide him.</p>
            <p>As it has pleaſed God therefore (pious Reader) to make me in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrumentall that ever this came to thy ſight, let me beſeech theſe two reaſonable requeſts of the. Firſt,
<pb facs="tcp:109976:4"/>That thou wilt paſſe no cenſure upon the Book or Writer, before thou haſt read all over, weighing the whole parts together, and examined them ſeriouſly by the unerring rule of the word of God. Secondly, Having ſo done, that thou wilt not ſuffer thy ſelf to be ſwayed from judging ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the truth, by any earthly reſpect whatſoever; and then I doubt not, but the Lord will ſuitably poure thee out a double bleſsing in the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding; of eſtabliſhment for thy judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and of peace for thy conſcience, which is the end of publiſhing this worke, and hearty prayer of the oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ſioner of it.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>I. C.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:109976:4"/>
            <head>An humble VINDICATION Of a Free ADMISSION Unto the <hi>Lords-Supper</hi>
            </head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Marke 14.23.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>And the all Drank of it.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Have ſpoken of the Inſtitution, Nature, and Ends of the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament; I come now to the Receivers, <hi>And they all drank of it.</hi> In the 17 <hi>verſe</hi> of the Chapter, we find the twelve with Chriſt; They were his whole Congregation; in the 18th. <hi>v.</hi>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:109976:5"/>They were all ſate at the Table; as they did eat (in the 22.) Jeſus took bread, and gave it them, and ſo likewiſe the Cup (<hi>v.</hi> 23) Saying, <hi>Drink ye all of it</hi> (<hi>Mat.</hi> 26.27.) And they did ſo ſaith the Text; <hi>They all drank of it,</hi> all the twelve without exception; from whence I gather a free Admiſſion to this Ordinance.</p>
            <p>My Brethren, this is a poynt we know troubles many, and I do humbly acknowledge my ſelf the weakeſt of a thouſand, to ſatisfie the difficulties of others; yet whereas the apprehenſions, many times, of a playn honeſt meaning Chriſtian, in its pure naturalls (I mean unconfounded with the judgements of others) may ſuit better with common underſtandings, than a more learned and elaborate diſquiſition; I ſhall Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerely propoſe my very heart and thoughts in this thing, being ready to lye down at the feet of any truly Godly Soul; that either out of tenderneſs of Conſcience, or ſtrength of Reaſon, dare not or will not, ſubmit unto my judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and practice in it.</p>
            <p>For the managing the poynt, I ſhall briefly lay down my meaning or
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:109976:5"/>ſtate of the Queſtion, give my Proofs, Reaſon, and Anſwer Objections.</p>
            <p>For my meaning it is honeſt, and very plain, without reſervation. The Lord Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus has a Church in the World, wherein there is a viſible profeſſion of his name; In this Church, God has ſet up his Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances of the Word and Sacrament. Of theſe Ordinances, ſome are capable, and ſome uncapable; Thoſe that are uncapa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, are ſo, either by Nature (who can diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne no meaning hereof) as Children, and Diſtracted perſons, or by the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches cenſure of Excomunication, and no others. For thoſe that are capable, we muſt rightly conſider this capacity, in regard of the Church (or Miniſter) in Admiſſion of them to the Ordinances; or in regard of the Communicants themſelves in coming thither. Now I dare not yet poſitively ſay for the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples part, that all are ſo capable that they may come as they liſt (though it be a duty none is excuſed from) becauſe there is a ſolemne preparation requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and many cannot ſeriouſly find in their hearts to enter; or renew their Covenant with Chriſt, whereof this is a pledge if it be not miſuſed. Yet I am
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:109976:6"/>humbly perſwaded for the Miniſter and Churches part, (who on Gods behalf is to offer Chriſt freely, and ſo to ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Covenant to all that will receive him) there is ſuch a univerſall capaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty for all men indefinitely, that if any come in, as profeſſing themſelves rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to enter Covenant with Chriſt, deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring ſo to ſerve him in the worſhip of this Ordinance (the former only excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted) we are to encourage them, ſaying with the Bride, <hi>Revel.</hi> 22.17. <hi>Whoſoever is a Thirſt let him come, whoſoever will let him come, and drink freely of theſe waters of Life, or means of Salvation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In a word, I do not believe that any, unleſſe firſt excommunicated (<hi>ipſo jure,</hi> or <hi>de facto</hi>) ought to be refuſed the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticipation of this Sacrament. <hi>They all Drank of it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For my proofs; look into <hi>Ex.</hi> 12. we read of the Paſsover, which is the ſame in ſignification with the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, <hi>v.</hi> 3. <hi>Speak unto Iſrael, let every man take his Lamb, a Lamb for a houſe. v.</hi> 47. <hi>All the Congregations ſhall obſerve it.</hi> And <hi>v.</hi> 50. <hi>The whole people did ſo as the Lord commanded them.</hi> Adde to this 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 30.5. <hi>The Decreed to
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:109976:6"/>proclame through all Iſrael from Dan to Beerſheba that they ſhould come and keep the Paſſeover to the Lord.</hi> Here you ſee free Admiſſion without exception. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed in <hi>Num.</hi> 9.7. we find a legall pollu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion keeping ſome back for a month and no longer, as it appeares in the 11 <hi>verſe,</hi> which nevertheleſſe was diſpenſable too at the prayer of <hi>Hezekiah,</hi> 2 <hi>Ch.</hi> 30.18. the reaſon being, becauſe ſuch unclean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe kept them from the Congregation (a plain type of the excommunicated on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly) but as for any ſpirituall pollution whatſoever (which is to be waſhed away with a penitent heart) we read of none that might debarre them from that Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance. This is that we ſtand upon: As for their legall rites, who knowes not they are aboliſhed?</p>
            <p>Now the Elder Brother (the Paſſeover) being dead, wee ſhall find the younger (our Sacrament) to have poſſeſſion of his inheritance in his free Adminiſtration. Turn to the 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.17. <hi>Wee being many are all partakers of one Bread.</hi> All; at <hi>Corinth</hi> there were many it ſeems, came over from Heatheniſm to the Church, and as many as came into them, <hi>All</hi> (this is the very truth) were admitted
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:109976:7"/>to their Communion.</p>
            <p>But now I pray, what <hi>All</hi> were theſe? ſee <hi>ver.</hi> 14. <hi>Flee Idolatry, I ſpeak to you, as men of understanding, judge ye what I ſay, is not this Sacrament the Communion of Chriſt, how then can you communicate with Idolls?</hi> This is the ſenſe in brief of the whole Chapter; mark it: Theſe <hi>Corinths</hi> were ſuch luke-warm Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, that they were ſometimes ready to goe to their Idolls, and ſometimes to Church; like thoſe in the ſecond of <hi>Kings</hi> 17.41. and happily thought it not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull. Now this Argument <hi>Paul</hi> uſes to reclame them; <hi>Doe we not All par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take of one Bread? therefore joyn not with Idolls. As ſoon as you come in to us wee admit, and joyn with you in our Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion, and profeſſion of Chriſt, (who is God) and therefore how can you with ſhame now goe to the Table of I dolls (which are Devills?)</hi> This is very force<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able and apparent, That theſe <hi>Corinths</hi> whilſt they are but willing to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs Chriſt, though yet given to Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry, are admitted with the reſt to the Sacrament, which very thing too, is urged as a means to reclame them from it: Compare this with 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.18. And
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:109976:7"/>there are the ſame <hi>Corinthians</hi> mutinous and even drunken together at this Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble; now this certainly was a great pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fanation, for which they are reproved and directed to examine, and carry themſelves better for the future; but as for their comming together. and gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall participation, that was but their du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and nothing is, or could be ſaid againſt it.</p>
            <p>Look back to 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.4, 5. There wee have the whole body of the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> that paſſed through the Sea &amp; Wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, Baptized under the cloud, &amp; drin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of the ſame Rock, Ieſus Chriſt; that is, admitted freely to both our Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. Take any Chriſtian, &amp; he will be ready to ſay, give me but any place of Scripture, or example of a generall Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion, and I will be convinced; Now here is one expreſſe, where all without exception, even thoſe very ſcandalous ones, with whom God was not well plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, but deſtroyed in the Wilderneſſe (while there was no legall Rites, ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all uncleaneſſe not forbidding any) do freely participate of the outward Signes one with another.</p>
            <p>Neither is it the ſaying this was a fleeting
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:109976:8"/>Ordinance, &amp; neceſſary to preſerve their lives, that can abate the ſtrength of this place, For doe we but mark the ſenſe of the Apoſtle, and you ſhall ſee in this very point, and to this very purpoſe does he parallell theſe Types to our Sacraments.</p>
            <p>The ſcope is this, Theſe <hi>Corinths</hi> were given to Idolatry and many vices, but yet thought well enough of themſelves, being ready to glory of their outward profeſſion, that they were of the Church, baptized, and communicating with Chriſtians: Now the Apoſtle to beat them off from this vain conceit, tells them plainly, <hi>I would not have you igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant</hi> (ſayes he) <hi>that All the</hi> Iſraelites <hi>were partakers of both theſe Sacraments, as wel as you, &amp; yet many of them were juſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deſtroyed when they ran to Idolls as you doe; and therefore take heed, and let them be a warning to you; As for theſe outward rites, they are things indeed, all that come to our Church, and profeſs Chriſt are admitted to, and ſo are ye, but yet think not you ſhall eſcape Gods Iudgments, if you walk not anſwerable to your profeſſion.</hi> The true importance of theſe words being well weighed, are ſufficient of themſelves to end this controverſie, the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:109976:8"/>ſenſe of Scripture, and not barely the words being Scripture.</p>
            <p>Turn to the parable of the Feaſt <hi>Matt.</hi> 22. with <hi>Luke</hi> 14.16.23. and though parables are not wholy Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentative, yet ſin their main purpoſe they are as inforcing as any Texts be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides; Now if this generall Admiſſion is not a chief thing intended, nay the very ſcope of the parable, judge by theſe particulars.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1 Firſt, In <hi>Luke</hi> there is no other thing added, but the calling of all unto the Feaſt is the main buſineſſe there ſet down only.</item>
               <item>2 Secondly, In <hi>Matth.</hi> where the ſtory goes on to the Wedding garment, unto the Maſters command is added the Servants bringing in all; both Good and Bad. <hi>verſe</hi> the 10th.</item>
               <item>3 Thirdly; The Lords very excluſion of him that came in to the Feaſt, mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſts he muſt be needs firſt admitted, and brought in by the Servants, his Sinne conſiſting not in his comming thither; for that he was compelled to doe, (by which I conceive is meant his duty) but in his neglect of putting on his Wed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding Garment; whereby it appeares by
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:109976:9"/>his unpreparedneſſe, he had no mind to come at all, if he could have help'd it</item>
               <item>4. Fourthly, Our Saviour explaines his own parable, ſignifying hereby that many are called, that is the worke of the Miniſtery, we are freely to offer Chriſt in his Ordinances: but few are choſen, that is the work of God, which we leave only to him. The Servants I ſay ſtill brought the man in, it was the Lord only took upon him to Iudge and caſt him out. Now who is that the faithful Steward that gives the houſhold their portion of meat in due ſeaſon, <hi>Luke</hi> 12.42. but theſe that are thus doing? 1 <hi>Cor</hi> 4.1, 2. <hi>Acts</hi> 20.28. even as <hi>Iohn</hi> Bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zes All that came to him for his Baptiſm, <hi>Mar.</hi> 1.5. <hi>Matt.</hi> 3. to the 11 <hi>verſe,</hi> though at the ſame time ſome of them he calls vipers (<hi>Adultis eadem eſt ratio u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triuſque Sacramenti,</hi> ſo that I take this a ſtrong proof with <hi>Iohn</hi> 3.26.) and as the Apoſtles themſelves, that when thouſands are converted at a Sermon, <hi>Acts</hi> 2.41.42. they immediately commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicate with them, diſtributing freely not only the meat of the word, but Bread too of the Sacrament.</item>
            </list>
            <p>See once more, <hi>Acts</hi> 10.28. A pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:109976:9"/>place I like for the expreſſion. Saint <hi>Peter</hi> here was very ſcrupulous of ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting Chriſtian Communion with any but the <hi>Iewes,</hi> it was a pollution under the Law to participate in any thing with the <hi>Gentiles, Io.</hi> 4. But being better in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed by a viſion from Heaven, God hath ſhewed me now, ſayes he, that I ſhould not call any man polluted and unclean; I thank the Lord I have lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned this ſame Leſſon with a ſatisfied Conſcience, to eſteem no man unclean, but all (unleſſe excommunicated) free in the uſe of Gods Ordinances Adde to theſe proofs the conſideration of ſuch Texts as ſet forth Free grace, as <hi>Iſa.</hi> 55.1. <hi>Rev.</hi> 22.17. <hi>Matt.</hi> 11.28.1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.4. <hi>I.</hi> 6.37. with the like; And tell me when the Goſpel offers Chriſt, or when Chriſt offers himſelf and grace, which are the things ſignifyed, thus freely to poor Sinners, how can we have the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience to turn them away from the Signs and means thereof in this Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>For my Reaſons.</hi> The firſt and chiefeſt I draw from the nature of the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. The Sacraments are <hi>Verbum vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibile,</hi> a viſible Goſpell; A declaring of
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:109976:10"/>Chriſt crucified; A Memoriall of the Covenant made by his death; that is, The Sacraments ſet forth Chriſt to the eye, as the Goſpel does to the ear; the ſame matter is preſented in both, only to divers ſenſes, and therefore the ſame latitude (I ſuppoſe us within the Church &amp; neither Infants, Fooles, diſtraught, (I may include drunk) or excomunicate) muſt be granted to them both in their adminiſtration.</p>
            <p>Upon this ground me thinks I ſtand as upon a Rock, againſt which all objections, like waves, doe but daſh themſelves in pieces. Look into the 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. we find Chriſt in the words of Inſtitution, ver. 25. telling us, <hi>The bread is his Body, the Cup is the bloud of the New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and the whole action, an ordinance in the remembrance of him.</hi> Now the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle comments on this in the 26 verſe, <hi>For as oft as you do it, you do ſhew forth</hi> (ſayes he) <hi>the death of the Lord;</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by you ſee plainly what is his judgment of our Saviours Inſtitution, whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver you may think of it, and that is to be a Declaration, ſhewing, or holding forth his death (or Covenant made by his death) unto the Receivers. This
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:109976:10"/>word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> this annunciation, or ſhewing forth is taken from the <hi>Iews, Exo.</hi> 12.26.27. who were to inſtruct &amp; declare the matter to their children at the Paſſover; ſo Chriſt is here ſhewed forth, as the matter of the Sacrament ſet forth, I may ſay, of God, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.25. as a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciliation through Faith in his bloud, to declare his righteouſneſs for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of ſins, alike in the Word and Sacrament. You have a place may fully expreſſe this for us: <hi>O ye Galathians</hi> Gal: 3.1. <hi>before whoſe eyes Chriſt hath bin ſet out as crucified among you.</hi> This expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion may be well applyed to the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, which doe ſo ſhew forth Chriſts death, that they deſcribe him crucified unto the ſight, and ſet him out unto the eye, that which the word declares him to the hearing. Now if there be any to whom the matter of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell may not be declared if there be any to whom we may not, or cannot ſhew forth the death of Ieſus Chriſt; if there be any ſtand thus excluded from the Church, that (without her mitiga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion) we may not tender to them the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, it is they, and they alone can be debarred from the Sacrament.</p>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:109976:11"/>
            <p>To this end we know the Sacraments are counted Signes and Seales, (and Seal indeed as Signes) now wherein is this but as they ſignify or repreſent the new Covenant to us, ratified in the bloud of Chriſt? Vnderſtand it thus; A man covenants with a Landlord about a purchaſe for his children at ſuch a prize, the price being paid the bargain is eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſht; This done he requires a writing, wherein the whole agreement is expreſly declared; unto this writing the Lord puts to his Seal to witneſſe the confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, and ſo it is deliver'd for his poſterity. Ieſus Chriſt does thus make a purchaſe for us, his death is the price he layes down to God for it, for convey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of this purchaſe, the writing that is drawn is the Goſpel, and the Seal put to this writing, is the Sacrament, both of which muſt goe, to make the publick In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument firm, that is to teſtifie the ratifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of it, and ſo it is delivered for the uſe of the Church.</p>
            <p>More fully thus; A Prince (by inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion of a Favorite) ſends forth a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamation of Grace to Rebels, upon con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of laying down their arms, and coming in to him, unto which he ſets his
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:109976:11"/>own Seal for their aſſurance. This Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamation is the word of reconciliation preacht, which runs conditionally to all, The Seal annext, is the Sacrament; now can it be imagined there is any to whom the Proclamation belongs, without the Seal? Is not the Seal publick as the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents of it? And ſo will it not be plain, that as we offer the conditions thereof to any, ſo likewiſe may we, and muſt we the Seal (upon their deſire) to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm them to come in, and ſubmit unto them? Thus we ſee the very nature of the Sacraments is as Seales to a Writing, to be but neceſſary appendices of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell.</p>
            <p>To conclude this firſt reaſon, then let me adde force to it briefly. in theſe foure conſiderations.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1 That we find that the Goſpell is to be preached to every creature, and a Baptizing them (which on the ſame ground in an orderly way includes this Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament with it) joyned as largely in the ſame Commiſſion.</item>
               <item>2 That as the Goſpell is to All, ſo it offers Chriſt freely; Now can any avouch, that a poor Soul may take Chriſt freely without qualifications,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:109976:12"/>(which is true is regard of any prece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent merit, ſo there be a preſent giving up himſelf to him ſincerely, as his Lord and Saviour) and yet let none but ſuch as are qualified to their mind, be Admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to receive him at the Sacraments? Is Chriſt offered as a free gift in the Word, and muſt we not come without our price and money to this ordinance? Why this is even as they conceive of <hi>Iudas,</hi> who being about to ſell our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour, went out to make his bargain, at the Supper.</item>
               <item>3 That the Goſpell-way is the beſt way to bring in Soules unto Chriſt. Let a Man be fully convinced of the free grace of God in Chriſt, his heart can ſtand it out no longer againſt his converſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Now when the word is preached, the Covenant opened, and the Seal too applyed, this Meſſage of recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciliation comes in its full vertue for the working this conviction, and faith unto Salvation.</item>
               <item>4 That the Goſpell is a peaceable Goſpell, an Embaſſy of Peace, now how ſhall this peace be kept, if where it comes, it goes to making ſeparati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons at this Ordinance? may a poor
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:109976:12"/>Soul ſay, O Lord Ieſus Chriſt, though I cannot lay claime unto thee as a Saint, I can as ſinner (I mean as a wounded ſinner) whom thou cameſt to ſave; and ſhall none but Saints apparent be ſuffered to come unto him hither? In a word, is the Goſpell peaceable, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verting, free, univerſall? What is the Goſpell but a declaring Chriſt Crucified? and what is the Sacrament in the Matter and Contents of it; but the very ſame? If <hi>Paul</hi> can tell us what it is 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.26. therefore there ought to be a free admiſſion to it, as to the Goſpell. Provided only I meane ſtill, that wee keepe within the ſtate of our queſtion and obſerve the generall rule of decency and order 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.40. which text forbids all confuſion (as to receive before one is baptized) and diſorder (all comming unworthily) in Gods Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, but not the Ordinances themſelves for ſome mens diſorderlines in them, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe there muſt be no ordinance at all allowed in this world.</item>
            </list>
            <p>My ſecond Reaſon I draw from the nature of the viſible Church; The vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible Church is a number of ſuch as make profeſſion of Ieſus Chriſt, and ſo are
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:109976:13"/>
               <hi>Saints by calling,</hi> whatſoever they are in truth; the eſsentiall marks whereof (whereby it ſubſits us viſible) is the Preaching of the Word, and Admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration of the Sacraments; now un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe Men will be ſo bold to diveſt our mixt Congregations (and ſo conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently all <hi>England</hi> formerly) of the name of the viſible Church, they cannot take from us one of its eſſentiall notes, in the free uſe of this Ordinance. This Reaſon may have invincible ſupport from Chriſts own doctrine and example.</p>
            <p>Firſt, His doctrine in thoſe parables of the little and great fiſhes in one net; The good and bad called to one feaſt, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore; The Chaffe and Wheat in one Barne; Eſpecially, the Tares and Corne in one Feild, <hi>Mat.</hi> 13. The Kingdome of Heaven is compared to that Field, and the Field (ſayes Chriſt) is the World, that is, the Kingdom of Heaven in the world, or the viſible Church cleerly in its Ordinances conſiſting of two ſorts of profeſſors, the Hypocrite, and the true beleever; which muſt grow together without ſeparation (even when the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants diſcerning the Tares, come and tell their Lord of them) untill the day of
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:109976:13"/>Iudgment; now who dare go to antici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pate that day, and enter upon the Throne of Chriſt? Lord is it thy mind we ſhould make the ſeparation between theſe Tares and the Wheat at one of thy Ordinances? I can never beleeve then, thou wouldeſt have left this parable ſo undoubtedly ſet forth in the Goſpell.</p>
            <p>Secondly, His example, not only in the frequent converſe with Publicans and Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, but even in this very thing we find him at the Paſſover, and his own Supper with <hi>Iudas.</hi> The three firſt Evangeliſts bring him in expreſſe with the reſt at Table, and as for <hi>Iohn,</hi> who wrote after the other, the truth is, (which many do not, or will not know) he find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this Supper fully ſet forth by them al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready, as in other things, he ſayes no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of it. St <hi>Luke</hi> is moſt evident, 22. <hi>ver.</hi> 21 where we read after the delivery, Chriſt ſays, <hi>Yet behold the hand of him that betrayeth me is at the Table.</hi> Yet, as if he ſhould ſay, Alas, though this <hi>Iudas</hi> partakes with us in this very ſupper, yet wil he go and betray me; So that a the ſame time, when he openly declares what a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probate or Devill he was (that this may not be poorely ſhifted off with his being
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:109976:14"/>a cloſe hypocrite) he not only waſht his feet with the reſt at a Supper a little be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, which <hi>Iohn</hi> only mentions, but here communicates with him both of the Paſseover and of this Supper. The e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence of which fact has ever appeared ſo fully to the Church, that this alone has been ground ſufficient to deduce their right of free Admiſſion; and what need more indeed be urged; but that men when they are willing not to ſee, will let any hand, put over their eyes be e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to blind them.</p>
            <p>My third Reaſon I take from the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of Chriſtian Communion, and Church-fellowſhip, which ought to be in Charity; in humility; <hi>without judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; every one eſteeming others better than themſelves,</hi> with the like in many places; eſpecially in the Miniſter, who is to be gentle to all, ſuffering the evill (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) to win them by this free way to Repentance, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.24.25. And how impoſſible is this, if we muſt go to cenſuring of mens worthineſs &amp; unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thineſs, preferring our ſelves, reje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting others? the ready way to nothing but heart-burnings, and diviſions, as we have too ſad experience already in moſt
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:109976:14"/>Congregation. To Give weight to this, remember three paſſages of our Saviours.</p>
            <p>Firſt, That of the <hi>Phariſee</hi> and <hi>Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lican, Luke</hi> 18. I need not relate it, only I beſeech you lay it to heart whether there be not ſomething (at leaſt <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5.22.) of the Phariſees, I thank God I am not like this Publican, in the turning away poor ſinners from this Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance. There is a proud, Phariſaiſme, I will not accuſe any of this, the very latchets of whoſe holy deſires (erring after a likeneſſe here to the Church in Heaven) I may not be worthy; and there is a ſtrict Phariſaiſme, as the Iews that were ſo rigid in their Sabbath, Chriſt was fain to rebuke and moderate them in it; Of ſuch a rigidneſs as this. I cannot but moſt ſorrowfully complayn in thoſe, that will not allow a free Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion. <hi>O my Saviour rebuke the humour of theſe times that is amiſſe, and moderate the zeal of all ſuch men, leaſt by their pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing a peculiar and ſuperstitious holineſſe on this Ordinance, they quite invert the charitable uſe of it and withhold the legacy thou haſt left thy people.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, That paſſage in <hi>Luke</hi> 6. When they murmured at him for eating
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:109976:15"/>with ſinners; <hi>the whole,</hi> ſayes he, <hi>need not the Phyſitian but the ſick, I come not to call the righteouss but ſinners to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance.</hi> O ſweet Jeſus, did'ſt thou alive offer thy ſelf and company to the very<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Publicans, and never caſtedſt out a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny that came to the, and ſhall we take ſtomach that thou art now thus offered at this Sacrament.</p>
            <p>The third place is in <hi>Jo.</hi> 8. When ſome ſevere Iews had brought a woman taken in Adultry, accuſing her by the law of <hi>Moſes</hi> that ſhe ſhould be ſtoned, Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus ſaid unto them, <hi>Let him that is with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſin himſelf, caſt the firſt ſtone at her.</hi> My Brethren, ſo ſay I, let a man examine his own heart, and if he does not find himſelf conſcious of the ſame corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; let him have a cenſure to caſt out others; for my part I muſt profeſſe the ſerious acknowledgement of mine own vileneſſe, makes me afraid at heart to turne away others, but I have learnt with Chriſt (<hi>Heb.</hi> 5.2.) to pitty them (as a fellow ſinner) by my own infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.</p>
            <p>My fourth Reaſon will ariſe from the vanity, formality, impoſſibility, of ſelecting people to this Ordinance. Look up but to
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:109976:15"/>the heart of all theſe ſeparations they come to nothing; For put the caſe, you will have a gathered company, I pray who do you account indeed to be fit and worthy receivers? If not all that make profeſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on as we do mixtly, then, thoſe only that have an intereſt in Chriſt, and are true be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers: Well, but how will you be able to know them? The heart of man is deceitfull above all things, who can know it? And if we can hardly diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover our own hearts, how ſhall we ever diſcerne others? So that all will come but to thoſe that have the fayr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt ſhew, thoſe that ſeeme ſuch, and you cannot be ſecured, but there may and will be ſome Hypocrites, and ſo this true partaking as all one body and one blood, in ſuch an unmixt Communion as you pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend, vaniſhes, and there can be no ſuch matter; But now if men ſtand here up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a formall purity, and will have the outward pureſt Church they can, they go to ſeparating againe, and never leave ſeparating and ſeparating (as we have dayly Teſtimony) till they are quite ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parated one from another; Even as in the peeling of an Onion, where you may peele and peele, till you have brought
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:109976:16"/>all to nothing, unleſſe to a few tears perchance, with which the eyes of good men muſt needs runne over in the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
            <p>My fith Reaſon I gather from the uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity of the Service of God; If all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther worſhip lies in common, it is an intrenchment upon the common liberty to put an incloſure upon the Sacrament. Are all the commands of God univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſall, why not <hi>Doe this</hi> alſo? If an unre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generate man cannot perform any thing that is acceptable to Chriſt, but is turnes to ſin <hi>(non perſe, ſed per pravam diſpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionem Subjecti)</hi> and ſo is Damnable, <hi>Pro.</hi> 28.9. and yet he is to doe his endeavour, and not to be excluded nevertheleſſe from any duty; why muſt there needs be an excluſion here upon fear of the like ſin and condemnation?</p>
            <p>Let men on one ſide anſwer, why do you allow a <hi>Syntax</hi> in the whole ſervice of God beſides; and bring in a <hi>Qua genus</hi> of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomolaes</hi> and <hi>Heteroclites,</hi> onely at this Ordinance?</p>
            <p>Let the other ſide anſwer, how can we admit of Children as Members of the viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Church, being born of Chriſtian pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, unto Baptiſme, and yet turn away the
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:109976:16"/>parents of thoſe Children from the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament? Thoſe that have gone about to anſwer this, had better happly have ſaid nothing. for our free courſe of Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme, and a deniall of this, is ſuch a Seam-rent, as will never be handſomly drawn up, though ſtitcht together; Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſs in yielding the one, they have granted the other.</p>
            <p>I will adde, whereas on either fide they have their formes, which they urge as <hi>Neceſſary</hi> (there being no admiſsion o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe) to a very joyning in the ſervice of God; let both anſwer, whether they offend not a branch of our Chriſtian free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome concerning ordinances of men <hi>Col.</hi> 2.18.20. which, though we might ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit thereto <hi>as prudentiall only,</hi> in the outward man, we dare not ſuffer <hi>to be ſet,</hi> or creepe <hi>into the ſeat of God,</hi> I mean the conſcience, that is in bondage if any religion be placed in them. It is ill putting Gods Worſhip upon ſtilts, which to advance it a little higher in the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward port, are ſure to give it a fall into dangerous ſcruples &amp; diviſions.</p>
            <p>My ſixt Reaſon I lay down from my innocency in this doing:
<list>
                  <item>1. I doe but my duty.</item>
                  <item>2. I have no power to turn
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:109976:17"/>away any:</item>
                  <item>3. I hope the beſt, of all:</item>
                  <item>4. I know God can turn the worſt even at this ordinance if he pleaſe:</item>
                  <item>5. I en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour my utmoſt <hi>de jure,</hi> that all come prepared:</item>
                  <item>6. I humbly confeſs all our ſins (as <hi>Hezekiah</hi>) deſiring true re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, and a pardon for all our omiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions; and ſo laſtly, I venture the iſſue all on God, knowing that his ordinances are a ſweet ſavour unto him, whether we are ſaved or periſh by them.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>I might adde here more conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons very preſſing, from the command, and good of comming; from the evill of omitting this ordinance.</p>
            <p>For the good of comming; The Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament is a means, and a pledge; a means as well to receive grace, as a pledge to aſſure us thereof: Now ſuppoſe a poor Soul wants grace, whether ſhall he come but to the means of receiving it? The ordinances are as the Baths, there are many come to the Bath, that are never the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter for it, yet as they are means of health they are open and free for all, to come, and make experience of them. I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive as much of the Sacrament, and though we may ſcruple how an unrege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerate
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:109976:17"/>man can receive it as a pledge, yet as it is a means whereby grace is convey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, there is no difficulty.</p>
            <p>For the evill of omiſsion; In the Law thoſe that neglected Circumciſion and the Paſſeover were to be cut off; &amp; in the Goſpell <hi>Matt.</hi> 22. thoſe that came not into the Feaſt, were deſtroyed, the Lord giving a reaſon <hi>ver.</hi> 8. becauſe they were not worthy. Alas! we make a ſcruple only of comming unworthily, whereas they are moſt unworthy of all that come not in to the Supper; we doe not find any of the Servants durſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe to call in all: if they had left out a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, they might have bin worſe ſerved. This one thing hath long ſtuck on my thoughts; how ſhall we neglect a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain duty of adminiſtring, or of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming to the Sacrament, for fear of acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentall ſcandall, or of committing an uncertaine ſin, in the doing? It not this a kind <hi>of doing evill,</hi> (the evill of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſsion) <hi>that good may come of it? whoſe damnation is juſt:</hi> Rom. 3.8.</p>
            <p>But I will ſay no more, thus much ſhall ſuffice, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> I will not give you my Reaſons by the heape, but by the weight; I humbly commit
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:109976:18"/>them to you, onely with this caution, that no man take occaſion from hence to preſume; for as the <hi>Iſralites</hi> (that were deſtroyed, after they paſſed the Sea, and drank of the Rock) are ſet for a warning to the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> ſo are they both ſet for a warning to us, that wee daily examine our ſelves, and come with reverence, leaſt we being freely admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by Gods goodneſſe, periſh never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſs with them for our own unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thineſs.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="sermon">
            <pb n="29" facs="tcp:109976:18"/>
            <head>The Second SERMON.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Ow for anſwering Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jections <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, Two things I muſt premoniſh you<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 1. Whereas common no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions are like diſhes, where the ſame matter dreſs'd but in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother way, or variegated in the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſsion, receives a ſeverall reliſh and eſteem in the palats of ordinary judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, you muſt pardon me the Liberty if at any time I be forced in the Cooke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of the ſame ſenſe to ſerve you in more words than enough to any Obje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction. 2. Whereas many Godly in theſe times have a prejudicate opinion a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt this free Admiſsion, ſo that what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:109976:19"/>may be ſaid, is not like to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move all ſcruples, which are ſo much faſtened on their Conſciences, thinking they have holyneſſe on their ſide; we are to goe unto the Throne of Grace, to pray the Lord to give us his Spirit of il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumination to direct us in this truth, which is able alone to convince and ſatisfie us. And as for me, if I deliver what is not conſonant to the holy Word, I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire the Lord to blot out my Sermon, with my ſin, that none of his Little ones may be offended by it; but if it be the mouth of Truth too much kept in ſilence, delivering nothing but the very doctrine and practice of Chriſt himſelf and his Apoſtles, (as one of his weakeſt ſervants does heartily beleeve) I hope the Lord will give a bleſſing on it, and ſend it out as a light into your hearts, to diſcover thoſe ſubtilities of Sathan, whereby he would obſtruct your comfort in the uſe of this Ordinance.</p>
            <div n="1" type="objection">
               <head>Objection <hi>1.</hi> This Doctrine will take away the uſe of the Keyes, Excommunicate Excommunicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and leave us no Diſcipline in the Church.</head>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:109976:19"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Vnto this by way of conceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, although it has been thought theſe cenſures belonged but to the Church, untill they had a Chriſtian Magiſtrate, I grant,</p>
               <p>Firſt, That there is a power of the Keys in the Church.</p>
               <p>Secondly, that the exerciſe of this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts in Excommunication.</p>
               <p>And thirdly, That the want there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of in the right inſtitution is to be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayled.</p>
               <p>But by the way of ſatisfaction, I Anſwer, this objection is grounded meerly on falſe ſurmiſes about Excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication, which being removed as the fewell from the fire, it will go out of it ſelf.</p>
               <p n="1">1 It ſurmiſes this Church-diſcipline to lye in ſuſpenſion from the Sacrament, as if Excommunication were but an Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communion.</p>
               <p>Let us therefore know, that theſe Church cenſures are puniſhments upon ſcandalous perſons (after a legall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viction) whereby they are debarred from Chriſtian ſociety in generall (leſt they leven others by their example) for els what is it to keep a prophane perſon
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:109976:20"/>from the Sacrament, but to gratifie him who never intended, at leaſt never ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, to come thither? But now when men will take theſe keyes that were made to the great Church doore, ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and ſhutting to all fellowſhip, and fit them only to the Chancell doore, as if they peculiarly belonged to this Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance, they many times get them in ſo far, that being unable to work them out again, they never leave turning and locking till they have both ſhut out the Sacrament from the Church, and the Church from the Sacrament.</p>
               <p n="2">2 It ſurmiſeth the inſtitution of this power to be in reference only to the Ordinances, to keep them pure and holy, as if the Sacrament eſpecially would be defiled otherwiſe to the recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers.</p>
               <p>Let us therefore further know the ends of theſe Church cenſures, that they concern not thoſe that are admitted to the Ordinance, but are uſed in reference only to Offenders, that there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by they may be kept in awe, and brought to Repentance. The only ends are <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> (as o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers have it) for their reformation,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:109976:20"/>ſatisfying the Congregation, and to warne others.</p>
               <p n="3">3. It ſurmiſes a moſt neer eſſentiall relation, between this Excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation and the Communion, as if it were a part of it; at leaſt ſome ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary Antecedence, as if the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment could not be Adminiſtred without it. Let us therefore diſtinguiſh final<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, between the exerciſe of the Keys as Acts of Diſcipline, and the uſe of the Ordinances as acts of Worſhip; and though the Keys may have ſome diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing power in regard of the outward or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of our worſhip, yet is there no al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyance in the nature of one another; one is in one Element, the other is in another? even as the Acts of the Aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zes may have influence on, but they have no relation to the nature of your private occupations.</p>
               <p>In duties there may be a double re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation; a relation of Ingrediency, as Faith has to Prayer, without which be in it, it cannot be effectuall; or a rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Subſerviency, as the Law has to the Goſpell, in being preparatory to it; now there is no ſuch relation at all, not only no ingrediency as a part of it,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:109976:21"/>but even no eſſentiall ſubſerviency, or dependance between Excommunication and the Sacrament. For what is the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion of another, to the communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of the Receiver? what Phyſical or Morall antecedence, has the puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of one at the Aſſize, to the worke in your ſhop, doing your trade? there is indeed a Key of inſtruction very re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite for our preparation, but as for theſe Keys of cenſures what can be more diſtant and impertinent, to thoſe that are coming hither? So that I judge there is no more reaſon for one upon this ground to ſay, I will no go to the Communion, becauſe there is not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communication, than for one to ſay, we have here no Iuſtices or Seſſions, we have no Magiſtrate in this Town to look to people in their dealings, therefore (becauſe it is better that we had) we will not live here but hold it altogether unlawfull to follow our ordinary voca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</p>
               <p>Rep. <hi>But is it not a heavy caſe we have no diſcipline eſtabliſhed?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> I ſay, true; but what then?
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:109976:21"/>therefore muſt we have no worſhip? <hi>Socrate ambulante fulguravit.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="objection">
               <head>Object. <hi>2.</hi> The moſt of men are wholy unfit and not capable of this Ordinance. This is enlarg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, Here are things to be done, Preparatory, a ſerious exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation; Executory, an exerciſe of Faith, Love, &amp;c. And here are things to be received, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion, Increase of Grace, Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurance, which all cannot obtain neither. Therefore no free Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion hither.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> There is a manifeſt weakneſs in this arguing from mens unability, to our duty. For as to the Churches part, in admiſſion of all (as I at firſt diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſht) who can but look upon at out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward capacity; here is nothing to them, no more than <hi>Iudas</hi> unworthineſſe and inward incapacity was to Chriſt. Let every receiver think what he has to doe. But as to the peoples part, I anſwer 3. things.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1, There is no duty a naturall man can perform rightly, ſo that moſt men
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:109976:22"/>are wholly uncapable to hear, to pray, or come to any Ordinances, where Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces are to be acted and receive, as well as at this Sacrament, but I hope that will not exclude them therefore from all, and give them a writ of Eaſe to doe no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing; I wonder grave men ſhould beat the ayr thus with a Feather.</item>
                  <item>2. I ſay to every man, though he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not doe what he ſhould and ought to doe, he muſt ſtill endeavour to doe what he can. The inſufficiency of any debtor (incurr'd through his own fault) does not diſcharge his Bond, but he is to pay what he can; it is every mans doing leſs than he can, that ſhall condemn him at the laſt day, ſay Divines; ſo ſay I, Let every man do what he can ſtill, and this is plain Divinity.</item>
                  <item>3. There may be a difference between a worthy Receiver, and a Receiving worthily; as a poor man (ſayes <hi>Pemble</hi>) though but unworthy to ſit there, may carry himſelf very worthily at the Kings Table. In this caſe therefore whoſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver thou art, doe thou labour thy beſt to prepare thy heart, and if after thy examination, thou judgeſt thy ſelf but unworthy, let thy humbled ſoul come
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:109976:22"/>and ſay nevertheleſſe, Lord, if I am unworthy, whither ſhall I goe to make me worthy? Is it not to thee my kind Saviour, that has an invitation <hi>(come ye laden)</hi> for the pooreſt ſinner? It is true, many count me but as a Dog, Lord I confeſs I am no better in my own ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion, but let even this poor Dog eat of the crums of thy Table. If I neglect my duty, I certainly offend thee, If I come Lord, I doe but humbly ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture on thy mercy.</item>
               </list>
               <p>Rep. <hi>But is not the Ordinance here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by taken in vain againſt the third Commandement?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> On the Receivers part when they find no benefit by it, they may judge ſo, and are find their fault, and repent of it; But not of the Admitters part, who are to doe their duty, and leave the ſucceſs to God; Even as Chriſt Preached to the people in Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, and gave only his Diſciples the privilege to underſtand them: And as all were ſuffered to touch Chriſt, when but one only received vertue from him; ſo doe I humbly conceive are wee to
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:109976:23"/>ſuffer all to come unto him here, leaving it to his breaſt alone, to give out the effectuall benefit, to whom he plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="objection">
               <head>Objection <hi>3.</hi> Holy things to holy men.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> There is a double holineſſe, an Inward, and Outward holineſſe; And this both in Things and Perſons: In Perſons, An outward holineſſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts in their bare profeſſion, and name of Chriſtian, and ſo are <hi>Saints by cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling;</hi> an Inward holineſſe conſiſts in the worke of Grace upon their hearts, and ſo are <hi>Saints by election.</hi> In Things likewiſe, The Ordinances are all holy, There is an Outward holineſſe in the Outward communication of them; There is an Inward holineſſe in the Inward Communion, vertue, power or efficacy of them, Now Outward holy things to Outward holy men, and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward holy things to Inward holy men; a viſible Ordinance to the viſible Church, and the inviſible Grace, to the inviſible Members that have a ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving intereſt in them by Faith.</p>
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:109976:23"/>
               <p>Rep. <hi>But doe we not hereby make our ſelves one with the wicked with whom we joyn, and can we have Communion with</hi> Chriſt <hi>and</hi> Belial?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> We doe, and muſt be one, with all that joyn in the ſame profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; that is, we are one, or one body, as Members of the ſame viſible Church in its outward capacity, freely adminiſtring the Ordinances, whereof we are to par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take; but we are not one with them in their evill diſcourſes, we diſclame them wholly in the impiety of their conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation. So that we have communion herein only with Chriſt, and have no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to doe with <hi>Belial.</hi> For I would not have any ſo groſly think, that a joy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning with a wicked mans perſon, is ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving a communion with <hi>Belial,</hi> but ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companying him in his evill wayes (<hi>Communio malorum non maculat quem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam participatione Sacramentorum</hi> (ſayes Auſtine) <hi>Sed conſentione facto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum:</hi>) If the <hi>Corinthians</hi> were alive, and you joyned with them in going to their Idols, this were indeed a commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:109976:24"/>with <hi>Belial,</hi> but if you only joyn'd with them in comming to the Lords Table, you ſhould partake of Chriſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, as the Godly of them the did, and as we ought to doe. I will goe with the wickedſt man alive to the Church, but I muſt leave him at the Ale-houſe; We may joyn with any to doe good, as to worſhip God in his Ordinance, to profeſſe, and confederate in Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity; but we cannot (that is we may not) joyn with any in the leaſt evill; we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſerve God and the Devil.</p>
               <p>But you will ſay further, Doe we not profeſſe the wicked, with whom we joyn, not only to be one of us, but one of Chriſt, and Partakers of his death? and how can we doe ſo? I anſwer very well. The viſible Church is the Body of Chriſt, as Chriſt ſaid, <hi>Every branch, in mee, that beareth not fruit. Io.</hi> 15.2. As <hi>Peter</hi> ſayes, <hi>There are ſome that deny the Lord that bought them.</hi> 2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.1. As <hi>Paul</hi> ſayes, <hi>There are ſome that are ſanctified with the bloud of the Covenant, which they trample upon. Heb.</hi> 10.29. (with <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.9.2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.14.) So ſay I of all ungodly profeſſors, They are ſuch branches in Chriſt, redeemed and
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:109976:24"/>ſanctified, in the ſame ſenſe as the Scriptures mean in theſe places; that is, in regard of a viſible eſteem, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by they externally partake of the Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances of Chriſt, and ſo are reckoned as Members of him.</p>
               <p>Let ſuch texts be laid a little more to heart, and when you have made the Orthodox interpretation the Queſtion will be even done, and we ſhall be no longer afraid of a free Admiſſion, when we muſt affirm, that there is an hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricall viſible faith, that gives an outward Church-right unto the Elements, as a true ſaving Faith, that gives intereſt to the effectual grace of the Sacraments; E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven as the branches have ſome union with the root, that bring forth only Leaves, though they partake not of that vitall ſap, that ſends forth fruit alſo.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="objection">
               <head>Object. <hi>4.</hi> the Seal is ſet to a Blanck, if All be admitted.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Unto this, which hath trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led many, I anſwer not preſently by the diſtinction of an Outward and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, an Abſolute and Conditional ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling:
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:109976:25"/>But I deſire a right underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of this Notion, how the Sacrament is a Seal taken up upon the Churches truſt. I have alwayes thought here lyes generally ſome miſtake, men take it to be a Seale unto their Faith, and if there be no true faith, it is ſet (they think) unto a blank, and this breedes a miſerable fear, to whom it is delivered. Let us know therefore (I propoſe it ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſively) that the Sacraments are not properly Seales unto our Faith. How doe we conceive Faith, ſuch a thing as muſt have Gods Seal put to it? God doth not atteſt our Faith, but the truth of his own promiſes, <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.17. but they are Seals properly of the Covenant: A Covenant is a thing muſt be ſealed, and the maker is to atteſt it thereby.</p>
               <p>Indeed they may be ſaid to be Seals of our Faith (as Divines ſpeak) <hi>conſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivè,</hi> by a conſequence of ſpeech, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe as Seales confirm a thing, ſo Faith is confirmed and ſtrengthened by recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving; which is an effect thereof, <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.18. but they are not <hi>Formaliter,</hi> for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mally in a true proper ſenſe, Seales unto any thing but the Covenant, or repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentations of the effectuall Seale, the
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:109976:25"/>bloud of Chriſt, by which it being rati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied with God, the Lord declares it by the Goſpell; unto the adminiſtration whereof, the Sacraments are ſet, to ſignifie the undoubted truth of it, as Seales (we ſay) and ſignes, ſhewing us, As the Bread and Wine is broken, pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red out, &amp; offer'd, with the other actions, ſo ſurely hath Chriſts Body been broken, his bloud ſhed, that all that believe in him according to this Covenant, ſhould have grace and ſalvation by him.</p>
               <p>And if it be to ſay more, God does hereby engage himſelf to make it good. The expreſſion is borrowed from <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.11. where Circumciſion is ſaid a Seal, not ſimply of <hi>Abrahams</hi> Faith, but of the righteouſneſſe of his Faith (or, of righteouſneſſe, I take it, through Faith: <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.9.) that he ſhould be the Father of them that believe, which thing ſealed to, is the very tenor of the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant. Now let Circumciſion be received on <hi>Iſaac</hi> the Child of promiſe, or on <hi>Iſhmael</hi> that muſt be caſt out, it is the ſame Seal of <hi>Abrahams</hi> Covenant; Let the Sacrament be offer'd to the Godly, or to the Hypocrite, it is the ſame Seal of God declaring the truth of his Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:109976:26"/>which ſtands moſt ſure, <hi>and all the unbelief in the VVorld cannot make it of no effect.</hi> Even as a Proclamation of pardon (as we inſtanced before) unto Rebels, comes with the Broad Seal to thoſe that refuſe it, and yet it is no leſs a true Seal, and ſet to a true writing, than if they did all come in and em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace it: ſo that if it want its due ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect on the Receiver, it may be ſaid (if you will) to be ſet upon a blank (where Seales are ſet) but not to a blank, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Lord hath ſet it, to the truth of his Word, or grace of his Goſpell.</p>
               <p>Rep. <hi>But were it not abſurd for a man to ſet his ſeal, when there hath been no agreement and tranſacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons before? So do unregenerate men, who come to the Sacrament without that ſolemn giving up the Soule to God, as he ought who enters Covenant with him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> I grant with ſorrow, there are too many of us come abſurdly, and but wickedly, when we forget to doe that we ought; the Lord forgive us:
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:109976:26"/>but though in the reciprocall action, as it is to be a ſeal (as is ſaid) of mans part, the receiver failes in his ſolemn mutuall ingagements according to the Covenant (whereof he is to repent,) yet as for the Miniſter, or Church, who offer it as ſeal on Gods part, there is a true ſeal to a true Copy, and nothing out of Order.</p>
               <p>The Sacraments therefore may be conſidered in their nature, and in their uſe: In their nature, I take them to be Gods ſeals only, as primarily ſignifying his grace, and ſhewing forth Chriſt, though in the uſe and effect they are to be mans too, as ſecondarily he is reciprocally to believe, and engage himſelf unto God: <hi>(Sacramenta noſtra accipimus ex manu dei, &amp; nobis ſunt ſignae gratiae primò, ſecundariò obligati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onis &amp; profeſſionis noſtrae. Paraeus in Loc. praedict.)</hi> In the notion they are mans ſeals, we may conceive the Sacraments Seals of Faith, for Faith is the conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Covenant, and we ſeal to our Condition, ſo that as they are concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved thus indeed, they are ſeals of Faith, becauſe ſeals of the Covenant, which I ſtand upon; But as they are Gods ſeals,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:109976:27"/>for the ſame reaſon they cannot be ſeals of Faith (but <hi>conſecutive,</hi> as I ſaid before, in regard of the effect to the Godly, to yeeld what (remotely and expreſſive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly) may be) becauſe God ſeals not imaginably to our part of the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant which is Faith, but to his owne part, which is the Promiſe, and ſo I call them ſeals of the Covenant or promiſe formally and not of Faith.</p>
               <p>Now I ſay cleerly, though an unrege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerate man cannot receive the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as a ſeal of his Faith, yet the Church can give it, as a ſeal of the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant; and though it wants its due ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect on him, there is the right nature nevertheleſſe in the Adminiſtration, though not a right uſe of it in the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiver; even as at the word, where there may be true preaching, and the nature of the Goſpell, though the hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers apply it not as they ought by faith.</p>
               <p>Look back to that only place <hi>Ro.</hi> 4. where it is ſaid Circumciſion is a ſeal, <hi>Abraham</hi> is ſaid to receive it as a ſeal, which receiving includes Gods giving, ſo that we muſt look upon the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in the nature of them, as Gods
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:109976:27"/>ſeals from the very inſtitution; who elſe durſt appoint ſuch things to ſignifie ſuch ſpirituall matters? and as they are Gods ſeals they are ſet to his own word, &amp; ſo can never be to a blank while there is truth in the promiſe, and writing in the Goſpell. Now then the Sacraments being Gods ſeals certainly, in the inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution and nature of them, if I ſhould deny them to be mans ſeals at all, there being not for it one tittle of Scripture, I ſhould quite remove the ſcruple from the hearts of men; but whereas (that I may not remove their care and duty too) I grant though in the nature of ſeals, they Gods Seals, Gods own Seals, ſeals of the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant only, yet in the uſe of ſeals and effect, they are to be mans ſeals alſo, ſeals to the Condition of our part, ſeals of Faith, and ſo I cannot, I may not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quit the receivers wholy, but that they come abſurdly, ſet a ſeal to a blank, and take the Sacrament in vain (as it is to be their ſeal) if they come without Faith, and thoſe ſolemn engagements as God requires of us: though I can fully acquit the Church herein, in her delivery of the ſigns on Gods part (as
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:109976:28"/>we are his Embaſſadors;) becauſe the Covenant by him ſtands ſealed to all whomſoever, and there can be no doubt of ſealing to a blank I affirm, ſo long as the Promiſe or the Goſpel it ſelf holds in force, the tenour whereof this Sacrament ſeals abſolutely to us. The te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of it I ſay, mark me, not our in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt in it; for that it ſeals not abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely. Aſſurance being concluded by way of diſcourſe, and whatſoever is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon to the Hypocrite with the beleever cannot conclude it. The Sacrament is the externall ſeal (the internall only of the Spirit (as witneſſing with our ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, <hi>Ro.</hi> 8.16.) can abſolutely give this intereſt to any) this outward ſeal, is ſet to Gods outward Copy of the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, that is the word; now look what the word affirms, the Sacrament ſeals, and confirms according to the tenour thereof, and no otherwiſe. Now the word ſpeaks not particularly of any mans ſingle intereſt, but generally it declares to all a common intereſt upon condition they beleeve; now as this inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt is expreſt conditionally, ſo the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament cannot ſeal to it but condition<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally, according to that tenor is expreſt;
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:109976:28"/>or rather let me ſay the Sacrament ſeals generally (ſo I will expreſſe it) the truth of the Covenant freely to all, engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them unto it, and the intereſt or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefits of the Covenant, to every ſingle perſon, upon the terms, conditions, or tenor only of the Goſpell.</p>
               <p>I muſt profeſſe this in the Embrion has layn a long time in my apprehenſions, and I cannot but be glad to find of late a pierc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing godly and excellent man (I take him) whom the right conceiving of this alone (he ſayes) converted his opinion and ſatisfied him.</p>
               <p>The Covenant runs thus, He that believes ſhall be ſaved, adde I believe; <hi>Ergo</hi> I ſhall be ſaved; from which ſyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logiſm we gather our aſſurance. Now to which of thoſe propoſitions (ſayes he) does the Sacrament ſeal? not to the minor as it is ſurmiſed, for no Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſayes of any particular man he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeves, and God ſeals to his own word, not ours. Nor to the Concluſion for the ſame reaſon. But to the major, which it abſolutely ſeals, as true to us, according to the tenour of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="objection">
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:109976:29"/>
               <head>Object. <hi>5.</hi> The Covenant belongs not to All, therefore the Seals neither.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> The Covenant is ſometimes taken in Scripture for thoſe abſolute promiſes of Gods putting his Laws in our hearts, keeping us by his power to ſalvation, and to the like purpoſe, <hi>Heb.</hi> 8. which are proper only to his Elect, and belonging to his ſecret will: Or the Covenant is taken as it is for the te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of the Goſpell in Gods revealed will, and ſo it runs on theſe terms, <hi>who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever beleeves ſhall be ſaved,</hi> and whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther this belongs to all, is no queſtion. It is true for our comfort; whoſoever comes under theſe conditions, may have an aſſured truſt, that the abſolute pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes alſo belong to him; but never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſſe it is the conditionall Covenant, or the Covenant in its conditionall ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacity, that is tender'd to us in the word, and ſealed to, in the Sacrament: So that the Covenant is indeed of the ſame extent with the Goſpell, and the very tenour ſhews it univerſally belonging to whomſoever.</p>
               <p>Now then, As when I have a buſineſſe
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:109976:29"/>to propoſe in generall to my Pariſh, I read the Contents, which when they like, I propoſe certain Articles, and ſay, who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever will agree to this, let them come and ſet their hands unto it. In like manner here, when I have held forth the glad tydings of the Goſpell, I ſhew them the conditions of the Covenant: Jeſus Chriſt offers life to all upon theſe terms of Faith; If you will reſolve to accept him as your Lord and Saviour, to forſake ſin, and ſerve him; come, put your hands and ſeals thereunto, in this Sacrament, &amp; loe here is the ſeal of God, on his part if you do, (to witneſſe the certainty of ſalvation promiſed to you) obliging him to his word. So that to ſpeak ſincerely, if wee ſhould pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe two men, one that is not in Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant with Chriſt, and one that is, this Sacrament doth more ingenuouſly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long unto the firſt, who hereby comes to do it ſolemnly at this time; ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, now he reſolves to enter Covenant with him. You will ſay, the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant doth not belong to him; What? Doth it lye upon his everlaſting dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation or ſalvation, and not belong to him? The benefit of the Covenant, you
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:109976:30"/>may truly ſay, belongs not yet to him, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till he is in Covenant, but the Covenant it ſelf is of Epidemicall concernment, and ſo far belongs to all, that it is to be ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered freely, and offer'd to them, that whoſoever doth receive it, may have the benefit of it.</p>
               <p>Rep. <hi>But what right doth this give him to ſhe Covenant?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> As the Sacrament is a ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing forth of Chriſt, with a tender of the Covenant in his bood, there is an open, free, generall right to it, for all that will come in to Chriſt. Let me beſeech you, mark this diſtinction; There is a dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble right here obſervable. A right of Obligation, and a right of Privilege: For the right of Obligation, in the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters offer of Chriſt freely, and the peoples receiving him in his own terms, I doe avouch a univerſall right, to eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Ordinance, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 66.23 they being dutyes of worſhip, which is of univerſall command (and this often, primitively once a week) though for the right of Privilege in any, to enjoy the ſweetnes, comfort, efficacy, life, and benefit of
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:109976:30"/>them, I acknowledge is it a perogative, belonging only to the Saints, and Elect of God.</p>
               <p>Now put caſe, a poor ſoul ſhould ſtand in doubt of his right to this Ordinance, that yet fain would come to Ieſus Chriſt. Let him ſay, Lord, My heart is humbly afraid of my unworthineſſe, yet ſeeing I come reſolving to give up my Soul to thee, and it is our duty to come in, at this Supper; This Right of Obligation ſhall be my warrant to bring me in, and then Lord I hope thou wilt let me find the Right of Privilege too, in thy due ſeaſon O my God.</p>
               <p>Put caſe again, A godly heart ſhould riſe at the conceit of a wicked perſon re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving with him, Let him think preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly thus, though there is a neerer Right unto my ſoul, bleſſed be the meer free grace of God, yet there is a Right of Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligation to every one, I ought not to be offended with any, the Lord ſanctifie it to them for their converſion. The knowledge of this plain diſtinction (with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the inveaglement here, of <hi>Adrem &amp; In re</hi>) may doe very much to allay the trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles of many Iudgments, and more Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences in this controverſie.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="objection">
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:109976:31"/>
               <head>Object. <hi>6.</hi> The Sacrament is not a converting Ordinance, we preach to all to convert them, but wee may Administer only to the regenerate, to confirm them.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Unto this Objection becauſe it is ſo much urged, give me leave to uſe ſome words. I doe acknowledge Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines do uſually diſtinguiſh, of a Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Initiation, and Confirmation, ingenuouſly attributing our new birth firſt to Baptiſm, and then our nouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and encreaſe unto the Supper, and ſo they make a converting Ordinance of the Word, and Baptiſm (the la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver and means of regeneration) and a confirming one only, of this Sacrament; although I take a grant of the one, to be a ſufficient <hi>medium</hi> to prove the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
               <p>But under favour, unleſſe this diſtinction be taken onely in regard of the outward viſible Church (into which, tis true Baptiſm alone does initiate, enter, or firſt incorporate us, and this ſupper con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm, or continue us as members there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of) we muſt underſtand it, not after a
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:109976:31"/>rigid form of ſpeech, and Idiome of truth, but after a more ſolute and inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuous conception; that is, it is ſuch a notion as holds full enough to be hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomely ſpoken, but holds not ſo ſtrictly as to build arguments on it, otherwiſe the ingenuity thereof will trip up their judgment.</p>
               <p>It is a rule therefore worthy here of our knowledge, that in divinity, we often give an indefinite denomination to things as they are moſt eminently in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clined; As for inſtance, in indifferent things (which are <hi>indifferentia ad u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num</hi>) when they incline more to evill in the uſe than to good (as many harm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe recreations) we condemn them indefinitely as evill, though in ſome caſes they are warrantable. <hi>Ec.</hi> 3.4 And I may happily with right circumſtances lawfully uſe them. So whereas this Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament doth more eminently incline to be, and is <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> moſt uſually confirming, and more ſeldome conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, they do <hi>à parte eminentiori</hi> deno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minate it indefinitely a confirming or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance onely. And indeed this is true when it is taken in reſpect of the ſame perſons, whom we ſuppoſing to
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:109976:32"/>have been converted by the Word and Baptiſm <hi>(ſuo modo)</hi> already, the Supper is, and can be only a confirming Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance unto them without queſtion. But as for others, who we conceive, not yet converted, and ſo humbly coming hither as wayting in the wayes of God for con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion, I doubt not, as there is no Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture to the contrary, ſo there is no rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, but as the Word and Baptiſm doe confirm, as well as convert; (the Spirit is not tyed to one meanes, <hi>Iohn.</hi> 3.8.) ſo may this Sacrament convert as confirm, according as God gives forth his grace to the Condition of the Recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers.</p>
               <p>There is therefore an error (to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer directly) in this Objection about the nature of the Sacrament (which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing as we have ſhewn) a viſible word holding forth Chriſt and the Covenant to the light, is converting, as the Goſpell doing the ſame to the hearing; for if the Centurion believed only by ſeeing Chriſt corporally on the Croſſe; if the contemplation of the Creatures, ſacrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, ſight of miracles, have been means, to ſome of their religion and converſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; wee cannot doubt, but the eyes
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:109976:32"/>may much more ſplritually inſtruct us here in the melting objects of Chriſts paſſion, redemption and tender mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies outwardly repreſented, ſeeing we hope the working of the Spirit too, by virtue of an ordinance. <hi>As at the word, Chriſt comes into the heart by the ſenſe of hearing, ſo at the ſupper by the ſenſe of ſeeing, touching and taſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Let the World Anſwer <hi>Pauls</hi> argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, To ſhew forth the death of Chriſt is the means of Converſion. The Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is the ſhewing forth his death. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.26. Therefore as it does ſo, it is undoubtedly converting, Hence I obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in the words of inſtitution, there was a <hi>Take</hi> and an <hi>Eat,</hi> two words, a <hi>Take</hi> for ſuch as have not Chriſt (a word of grace) to convert thoſe: and an <hi>Eat,</hi> for ſuch as have already recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved him, to nouriſh and confirm them. For, put caſe, a morall man, taken for a good man, yet unregenerate, is, and cannot be refuſed to be, admitted hither: The man does his beaſt to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare himſelf, and ſo comes; doe wee think now, to ſuch a man the Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance is neceſſarily fruitleſſe, and can
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:109976:33"/>have no work on him? then God help us. Shall not his examination, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, prayers, meditation, with all the Miniſters exhortations, be more ſolemnly conducing now, to work grace in his heart, and to convert him (this being the way of the ſpirits moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons) than the bare preaching of a ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon? Eſpecially ſeeing the word doth not only precede, but accompany, and is a very part too, of the Sacrament. <hi>Accedat verbum ad elementum &amp; fit Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramentum.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But, put caſe further, a poor Soul much humbled in the ſight of his ſinnes that cannot yet be able to believe and cloſe with Chriſt, comes hither, hoping to meet with this favour here; well the word of reconciliation is freely ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, the free mercies of Chriſt ſet forth, and all this while it hath not happily this effect upon his heart, yet when he comes to ſee the truth of all this ſealed with Gods own ſeal, Chriſt freely offered, and peculiarly received of him in the Sacrament, his Soul by all theſe heavenly wires is catcht, taken, drawn, and even enforced to a ſaving Faith; the Spirit uſing ſuch moſt powerfull
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:109976:33"/>methods, for the work of his grace, which he infuſeth in us, by a ſweet at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temperation to the will, not by compul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, <hi>habitus infuſi,</hi> being wrought <hi>per modum acquiſitorum.</hi> And this we have lively repreſented in the two Diſciples of <hi>Emmaus</hi> whoſe hearts did burne within them at the hearing of Chriſt, but at the breaking of bread their eyes were fully opened to know and to believe him, <hi>Luke</hi> 24.30, 31.</p>
               <p>Rep. <hi>Although a Man may be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted At, it is not By the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, it is occaſionally, but not intentionally a converting Ordinance.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> This being undeniably granted of our oppoſites, the matter is upon the point yeelded; for conſider ſincerely this: It may be, Peradventure a man may be converted by it, and no text ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly forbids any comming to it; is not this enough? An <hi>It may be</hi> granted, (lay it wel to heart) and no place to the contrary alleged, who doubts not but all <hi>It may bee's,</hi> all occaſions muſt be taken for our ſalvation?</p>
               <pb n="60" facs="tcp:109976:34"/>
               <p>But that I may wholly root out this ſubtility, which I think the ſpirit of error has inſinnuated in the hearts of many Godly men; I have three things more to ſay, which by Gods bleſſing will fully do it. Provided, if the thing ſerves our turn you will not be grating on the expreſſion.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Let us cleerly know, that the Sacraments, and all Ordinances, are primarily and properly means of grace; It is but in a remote ſenſe, they are means of converſion, or confirmation. For this grace we receive in the uſe of them, is that which convert ſome, and ſtrengthens others. Now then we come to this Sacrament, as the means to receive Gods grace, and this grace, which he diſtributes as a moſt wiſe God, works in every one, as his ſtate and need requires; in the converted for their ſtrength and eſtabliſhment, and in the unregenerate for their conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Conſider what is Converſion. There is an outward converſion from Heatheniſme, to the profeſsion of Chriſt; wee doe not ſtand to ſay the Sacrament is ſuch a converting Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, as if Chriſt ſhould bid us goe
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:109976:34"/>forth with this Sacrament, and convert the Nations, let this be imagined only of the word. But there is an inward effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuall converſion of ſuch as outwardly profeſſe Chriſt, to the truth of grace in their hearts. Now how is the worke of grace (or true converſion) wrought through the word it ſelf? Not from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny active power it has <hi>per ſe,</hi> upon the Soul; but <hi>per modum objecti</hi> we ſay, and inſtrumentally: the object is propoſed or revealed, that is all the word does, and then it is the Spirit that by illumina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the mind, and the touch upon the will, brings the heart to embrace the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, whereby it is converted. Now is it not juſt thus likewiſe in the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment? This Sacrament ſhews forth Chriſt Crucified according to the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, who is the true object of Faith and Life, upon this the Spirit of God draws the heart (by illumination and conviction) to embrace him upon thoſe terms he here is offered, inſomuch that experience can witneſſe that ſome are, and have been hereby converted. What difference is there imaginable between this converſion, and at the Word? what a ſhift is it to ſay it is only At, and not
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:109976:35"/>By the Sacrament, when it is inſtrumen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall (morally we mean, not phyſically) <hi>per medum objecti,</hi> as the Word? where I may ſay the ſame too as truly, that it is more properly At, than By, the Word it ſelf, there being no active vertue but of the Spirit, in the one, or the other.</p>
               <p n="3">3. As for this ſcruple of the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment being occaſionally, not intentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally converting; There may be a prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall intention and ſubordinate; more primary, or ſecondary ends in an Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance: Though the word be the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal converting Ordinance, we cannot deny but others may be ſubordinately alſo converting, as Prayer; why els doth the Church pray, <hi>Turn thou us, and we ſhall be turned, Convert thou us, and we ſhall be converted?</hi> Now as Prayer and other means of Grace are conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, and that intentionally in being uſed to this end; So I affirm of the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, unleſſe you can find in your heart to keep this pitifull ſhift ſtill, and ſay, rather than this ſhall be, you will diſtinguiſh between a converting ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance and means of Converſion, other ordinances are means of Converſion, but yet the word, you perſiſt, is the only
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:109976:35"/>intentionally (that is intended) conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting ordinance: Well; goe too, what then I pray? To the purpoſe. Then you wil ſay the word ſhall be held forth to all as intended to convert them, but the Sacrament ſhall not, being not ſo intended in the Inſtitution: Be it ſo: It followes then, there muſt be no Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance adminiſtred to thoſe that are not converted, but only that which is thus an intended converting Ordinance: Is this as you would have it? This is the very ground on which you ſtand: But hark ye, my Friend, I pray then what ſhall become of publick prayer &amp; other Ordinances in the Church, when the Word is the onely principally intended converting Ordinance out of queſtion? By this doctrine at one daſh you take away all other duties in our mixt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregations: In what a caſe are you here brought? what can you invent? On neceſſity you muſt recant and confeſſe indeed, that Prayer and the like duties, though not principally, yet in a ſubor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinate way are converting Ordinances, or means and helps of converſion; and upon that account you admit all to them: Now if you will doe ſo, then is
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:109976:36"/>the door as full open in this ſubordinate way too, for the Sacrament: If you will not, I beleeve the Sacrament will be contended to be ſhut out with ſuch good company, and deſires to fare no better than her fellow-ordinances.</p>
               <p>Rep. <hi>But unregenerate men (you will ſay) are dead in their ſins, and ſhall we give bread to the dead? men muſt firſt be living, new born, and converted Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, before they can feed at the Sacrament?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> As for the ſenſe of this, it is anſwered already, as for the words and Fancy, I return accordingly. If wee could conceive any bread to be ſuch, as would fetch life in a man, wee ſhould give it him when he is dead; but now ſee <hi>Io.</hi> 6.33. <hi>I am the bread of life,</hi> ſayes Chriſt, <hi>not only</hi> (I hope) <hi>to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm, but give life;</hi> Now Chriſt being offered in this Sacrament, this bread, is the bread of Life, this cup, the cup of Life, able by Gods grace as well to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get Life, as increaſe it. If we give <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qua vitae</hi> to dying men, we may give
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:109976:36"/>
                  <hi>Calix vitae</hi> to dead Chriſtians, to quicken and convert the unregenerate, as to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort and eſtabliſh others.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="objection">
               <head>
                  <hi>Object. 7. Judas</hi> received not the Supper, for in <hi>Mat. 26.23.26.</hi> he is ſaid to dip his hand in the diſh before the adminiſtration, &amp; in <hi>Io. 13.30.</hi> as ſoon as he recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved the Sop he immediately went out. Beſides ſome learned men conceive the Sauce he dipped in, was the Sauce of bitter herbs in the Paſſeover (cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Cheroſeth</hi>) and that was therefore before the Sacrament.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Here is a manifeſt miſtake in the ground of the objection. It is ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed St. <hi>John</hi> ſpeaks of the Paſſeover Supper, as the other Evangeliſts, but ſee the firſt verſe of <hi>John</hi> 13. with verſe 29. and it is expreſt, <hi>Before the feaſt of the Paſſeover, Supper being ended;</hi> as if he ſhould ſay, As for the Sacrament Supper at Paſſeover, the other Evange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſts have fully ſpoken, but there was a Supper a little before, where there was remarkeable theſe paſſages they have o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, and ſo he relates a waſhing the
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:109976:37"/>Diſciples feet, and other things that were not to be done at the ſolemnity of the Paſſeover, for the feet were to be ſhod then, &amp; the like geſtures quite contrary: <hi>Ex.</hi> 12.11. But if (as ſome ſay) thoſe paſſages which noted their haſte out of <hi>Egypt,</hi> were not obligatory when they came to the Land of Reſt, yet ſo large a circumſtance as is here mention'd of <hi>Iohn,</hi> to be introduc'd of Chriſt at that time is not probable.</p>
               <p>See <hi>Io.</hi> 12.1. There Chriſt came to <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thanie</hi> ſix dayes before the Paſſeover, where abouts he ſtayed that time (going ſometimes to the City to preach, <hi>Mar.</hi> 11.17.19. and back again) it being neer the Mount of <hi>Olives,</hi> which he did then frequent. <hi>Luke</hi> 22.39. In this ſpace he rode to <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> on an Aſſe, and came back at night. <hi>Mar.</hi> 11.11. Now this night happily, or thereabouts, was this Supper <hi>John</hi> mentions, where <hi>Judas</hi> having received the Sop, went from thence, to agree with the Prieſts, the Devill then putting it into his heart. <hi>Luke</hi> 22.1, 2, 3, 4, <hi>When the Paſſeover drew neer,</hi> mark it, <hi>Then entred</hi> Sathan <hi>into</hi> Judas, <hi>&amp; he went &amp; communed how he might betray him.</hi> Then when it drew neer, that is about a night before, or juſt
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:109976:37"/>two nights, comparing this with <hi>Matt.</hi> 26.2.14. <hi>Mar.</hi> 14.1-12. So that it could not be at the time ſuppoſed, that is ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt.</p>
               <p>Now on the morrow, or two dayes after this, Chriſt went from this <hi>Betha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny,</hi> again to <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> (which was ſome 2 miles thither) it being the day of the Paſſeover. [Whether Chriſt kept it the ſame night with the Jewes, I need not controvert, ſeeing he kept it certainly the firſt day of the Feaſt, <hi>Matt.</hi> 26.17. <hi>Exod.</hi> 12.16. and the time when the Paſſeover was to be kill'd <hi>Lu.</hi> 22.7. <hi>Mar.</hi> 14.12.] There according to the Law, he eat that Supper with the Twelve, and inſtituted his own. <hi>Mat.</hi> 26.26. Now here was <hi>Iudas</hi> amongſt the reſt, ſitting together with them at the Table till all as done. <hi>Luke</hi> 22.21. And when they were riſen, Chriſt with his Diſciples going again to the Mount of <hi>Olives, Iudas</hi> ſtole away (happily in the dark) to fetch the Officers according to his agreement, and betrayed him. So that Chriſt forewarned his Diſciples twice of <hi>Iudas</hi> Treaſon, the night or two before, by giving him a Sop, with which <hi>the Devill entred his heart</hi> at firſt, to ſet him upon his bargain; if you
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:109976:38"/>conſider well <hi>Io.</hi> 13, 27, 28, 29, 30. with <hi>Luke.</hi> 22.3, 4. and here at the time of his own Supper with a like <hi>Item</hi> again, by dipping his hand with him in the diſh; A like I ſay, not the ſame; for St. <hi>Iohns</hi> giving him the Sop is not the ſame thing, as not at the ſame time, with Saint <hi>Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thew</hi> and <hi>Marke's</hi> dipping in the ſame diſh. That I ſay being before the bargain (while it was to do, <hi>that thou doeſt do quickly</hi> ibid. 13.27) this at the very time of accompliſhing it; (being already a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greed, and ſo in effect done, <hi>verily the Son of man is betrayed,</hi> Mat. 26.24. with <hi>Luk.</hi> 22.22.) Neither may the Diſciples ſecond enquiry <hi>It is I,</hi> Scruple us herein, if you but ponder what <hi>Iohn</hi> addes uppon this, ver. 28. and <hi>Luke</hi> 18.34.</p>
               <p>As for many learned mens thoughts about the Sop and the Supper, whether there was one two, or three, this night, I leave only as conjectures, wherein they may erre as they have likely done in this, and ſo not to be built upon; and foraſmuch as <hi>Iudas</hi> was at Table, by the teſtimony of 3 Evangeliſts, me thinks their witneſſe ſhould be ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient for his receiving; but when it ſhall be conſidered too, that the fourth is ſo far from ſaying any thing againſt it, that he ſayes nothing of this Supper
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:109976:38"/>at all, they having ſufficiently done it already, I hope this objection will trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Folkes no more.</p>
               <p>As Chriſt offers himſelf to thoſe that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed him, <hi>You will not come unto me, that you may have life. I would have gathered you, and you would not.</hi> As Chriſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſes with thoſe that could not profit, <hi>You underſtand not, Io.</hi> 8.43. <hi>becauſe you cannot hear my words.</hi> And as Chriſt when he preaches to all freely, ſayes, <hi>He that hath ears to hear, let him hear;</hi> So does he adminiſter this Sacrament to <hi>Iudas</hi> amongſt the reſt, and ſo do I ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſter it to all, ſaying, <hi>He that can re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, Let him receive it.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="objection">
               <head>
                  <hi>Object. 8.</hi> Vnworthy Receivers are guilty of Chriſts blood, and eat their damnation, therefore wee muſt not allow a free Admiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Unto this I ſhall ſpeak Firſt on the Churches part, and Secondly, on the Receivers.</p>
               <p n="1">1. For the Churches part, I mean the Admitters (if the term takes place with us) and Ioyners; I do verily beleeve, let men urge what they will, this can never
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:109976:39"/>be made any way to concern the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. There is a generall command. <hi>Doe this,</hi> every one is to examine himſelf and to come worthily, if they doe not, they receive their own damnation (<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.29.) they receive not ours, who do our duty as we are bound, and leave others unto God.</p>
               <p>Rep. But you will ſay; <hi>If another ſhould be taking a cup of poyſon ſhall not we be partakers of his bloud, if we doe not hinder and forbid him?</hi> Qui non vetat, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>I anſwer, (beſides that we have no <hi>Quum poſſit</hi>) it is a wonder to me any religious man ſhould compare this Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament to a Cup of Poyſon, ſeeing it is in its own nature a Cup of Bleſſing, and if it prove death to any (as Sin may take occaſion from the Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and ſlay us) through their own impiety; it is more than we can know, or ought to judge, ſeeing God is able to make it (as it is) a Cup of Salvation, even to the worſt. Let us act with chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table thoughts, and leave the ſucceſſe to God. Even as <hi>Paul</hi> in his preaching,
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:109976:39"/>who in 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2: tells us, <hi>It was the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of death unto ſome,</hi> ver.16. <hi>yet muſt he preach it in every place,</hi> ver.14. <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it was nevertheleſſe a ſweet ſavour unto Chriſt, in thoſe that periſh'd, as in thoſe that were ſaved,</hi> ver. 15. So ſay I of this Sacrament, we muſt doe our duty and adminiſter freely, knowing God will make all his ordinances a ſweet ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to himſelf, whether it be of life un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to life, or death unto death to any of us.</p>
               <p n="2">2. For the Receivers part, there is a double duty; A principall. <hi>Doe this:</hi> And an acceſſory, <hi>Let a man examine himſelf.</hi> We are bound to come, and to come worthily; If a man failes in the one, and is not ſufficiently prepared; I dare not ſay, that muſt keep (I am ſure it will not excuſe) him from the other. This is cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain; thoſe dreadfull expreſſions of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing guilty of Chriſts bloud, and drink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing damnation, are to make men take heed that they prepare themſelves and come worthily, but I cannot think they are to affright any man from the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. There are 3 <hi>Quaere's</hi> therefore I will ſubmit here to further conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
               <pb n="72" facs="tcp:109976:40"/>
               <p>The firſt, whether the very eating and drinking of an unworthy Receiver be damnation, that is, (to free ſome weak minds from fearfull thoughts) whether it be ſuch a ſinne, as makes a man guilty (without repentance and Gods mercy) of Condemnation? And I conceive we muſt diſtinguiſh between the very receiving, which is good; and the unworthineſſe, which makes the ſin only. This unworthineſſe is in the Perſon, or in the Act: In the Perſon it conſiſts in his evill conſcience, which will condemn him whether he comes, or abſtaines from comming. Put caſe one receives not, and is unworthy, the guilt of his unworthineſſe lyes never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſſe upon him for that, it may be, more; for in this very refuſing, his own Conſcience condemns him, and God is greater than his Conſcience, whereas if he comes, it happily may excuſe him ſomething in not neglecting the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward performance, not aggravate his condition; for though he failes in the inward, and that failing is ſin, yet that Act he does makes him not more ſinfull for the doing, but he would have ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned more to have failed in that too, and not have done it. Unworthineſſe in the
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:109976:40"/>act, conſiſts in the obliquity, deficiency, or failing in the right manner of receiving, though the outward work it ſelf be not amiſſe. There is the matter of a duty, and manner; As for the matter, every one can doe, in a Chriſtian deportment at the Table, but in the manner, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive in Faith, Love, and other graces as we ought, this a naturall man cannot doe, and ſo he ſinnes in his duty. His very Act is not ſinne, ſo far as he does doe in the matter it is good (not only <hi>ſub genere entis,</hi> but good <hi>in tanto, ſub ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nere morum</hi>) but this failing and ſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving in the manner, is the evill, which as it cleaves unto, we may conceive, defiles the Act, and makes it lyable unto judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
               <p>Now then my ſecond Quaere is, Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther receiving the Sacrament unworthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, is otherwiſe damnable, then pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and hearing unworthily; (whereof Chriſt ſayes as much, <hi>Go and preach, he that bele<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>eth not is damned, Mar.</hi> 16. <hi>Iohn</hi> 3.18. <hi>ipſo facto</hi> as much as here) And if it be not, why upon the ſame ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, as men goe to prayer, to the word, and other dutyes, though they cannot pray and hear worthily, they may not as well goe to the Sacrament? my thoughts
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:109976:41"/>are thus; It is a ſad <hi>Dilemma</hi> unregene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate men are in; If they pray, hear, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, they ſinne (not in what they doe, I conceive, but in what they not doe) by failing in the manner, their perſons being not acceptable; If they doe not pray, hear and receive, they ſin worſe and are impious. Now what muſt be done here? If there be a neceſſity of ſinning, of two evils the leaſt muſt be choſen: its a leſſe evill to doe what we can, though the outward matter on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be done, than to fail in matter and manner too, wholly caſting off the care of God. But if that axiom be true, <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo anguſtiatur ad peccandum,</hi> there is no caſe wherein a man is neceſſitated to ſin, (and ſo that ſaying <hi>Of two Evills,</hi> muſt be taken alwayes <hi>de malo poenae,</hi> not <hi>culpae, Rom.</hi> 3.8.) then it is moſt clear, Every man muſt come and do the beſt he can, which if he doth happily he ſhall not ſin at leaſt ſo far he does not) and God may bleſſe his endeavours, <hi>Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>benti dabitur,</hi> whereas if he neglects, he ſinneth without queſtion, this being <hi>ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum perſe,</hi> the other <hi>per accidens</hi> onely. I will be bold therefore to diſtinguiſh: there may be a profane, preſumptuous coming to an Ordinance, or a Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:109976:41"/>coming in conformity to Gods wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip; though it is better not to come, than to come in a profane way, this be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing rebellion and ſin in the fact; yet I ſay clearly, it is better to come in a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian way, though but in an outward co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity to Gods ſervice, than altogether to neglect it; which being granted and practiſed of all in other duties, I think it but a begging the queſtion, to deny it in this Sacrament.</p>
               <p>My third Quaere is, Whether an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>regenerate man conceiving himſelf not worthy, muſt never come to the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, for fear of eating his damnation. And herein my thoughts are apt to run comparatively on the word; The word ſets forth Chriſt on the termes of Faith and new obedience, that is the Goſpell rightly adminiſtred, whatſoever effect it hath on the hearers; Now it is their part indeed to receive and apply it by Faith, if they doe not, it pronounceth them damned; Thus the Sacrament like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe ſhews forth Chriſt unto the ſight; and for the Churches part ſhe is to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare and offer him to all, however he is received: Now the receivers, 'tis true, in the like manner again are to receive in Faith as they ought to doe: If they
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:109976:42"/>receive unworthily, as the word de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounceth, this ſeals to their damnation. Now a man will ſay, if the word pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounceth may damnation, ſo long as I am an unworthy hearer, I will not goe thither, I ſhall but hear my damnation; but I ſay you muſt goe thither, you lye in a damned ſtate already, and it is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary this damnation ſhould be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced upon you, to awake you out of your ſecurity in it, that by the terrours of Conſcience you may be driven to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent and be converted; ſo the word is good in it ſelf, and the ſavour of life e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven while it damns a man, if he uſefully receive it: ſo ſay I of the Sacrament, it is good in its nature, it is appointed for our good, and ſo wee are to come unto it, as a means of grace; but if it acciden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tally ſeals to any man his damnation, it is through his own unworthyneſſe, and he is then to make the ſame uſe of it, as of the damning word, that laying to heart the horror of his ſinne, in being guilty of the bloud of Chriſt, he may be provoked thereby to fly to Ieſus Chriſt, for a merit of his bloud to waſh away his guilt of it; and having receive ſo many ſeales of his damnation, he may be forced to the Lamb who alone is able to
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:109976:42"/>open all thoſe ſeals, by pardoning his ſins, and ſo to turn the ſavor of death unto life, and to make even damnation it ſelf (ſuch is the power of his grace) ſubſervient to his converſion and ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. I ſumme up this: If comming unworthily makes a man guilty of Chriſts blood, by powring it out in vain, what ſhall an open refuſing deſerve, that even tramples upon it in the deſpiſing this or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="objection">
               <head>
                  <hi>Object. 9.</hi> The Ordinance is polluted if all be admitted.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Unto the unworthy receivers, it may be ſaid defiled, in that ſence, as all things elſe are to the unbeleevers, whoſe conſcience is defiled, that is I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive in ſinning in all that he does <hi>Tis.</hi> 1.15. But unto the admitters (unleſs they be convicted) and joyners (who (as the Schools ſay well) concurre in their <hi>Actu phyſico,</hi> not <hi>morali,</hi> to their act of receiving, not unworthineſs) their minds being pure, All things (even the worſt) are pure, and there is no more reaſon to be afraid of comming for that unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thineſſe of another, than for a man to ſcruple likewiſe, becauſe the cloath is
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:109976:43"/>not clean enough upon the Table.</p>
               <p>Indeed in the Law we read of a diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhing the clean from the unclean, <hi>Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vit.</hi> 10.10. &amp; 11.47. which otherwiſe would defile their Sacrifices. <hi>Hag.</hi> 8.14. and their very Temple. <hi>Ez.</hi> 23.38, 39. Such an outward holineſſe had their le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gall Rites, that it could be touched, but the holyneſſe God now requires is more inward certainly, and to be laid up clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer in the heart, than that the externall holyneſſe of another ſhould come at, or reach it: We muſt conceive under the Goſpell, all this legall holineſſe, in pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, perſons, things is abrogated, ſo that there is nothing unclean now unto us. <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.14. which thing was ſhewed <hi>Peter</hi> in a viſion; it is pity men had need of another to mind them of it. But that all ſcruple may be removed, Chriſt has left it in plain words, <hi>Nothing with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the man, defiles the man,</hi> Mar. 7.15. <hi>and nothing that enters into the mouth;</hi> as if he would meet with this in particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar, <hi>Matt.</hi> 15.11. If the heathen hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band be ſanctified to the beleeving wife, which is the neereſt communion that can be, 1 <hi>Corinth.</hi> 7.14. ſo that ſhe muſt not ſeparate from him in the duties of Marriage, as it is Gods Ordinance, I
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:109976:43"/>may reſolutely ſay, it is not the unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thineſſe of another, ſhall make the true beleever ſeparate from the Sacrament, but even the vileſt that comes there, are <hi>ſanctified to him</hi> (<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>) that is, are clean in reſpect of his communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting with them, ſo that their wickedneſs, being an externall thing to him, cannot defile his duty. This is the privelege (I take it) of the Goſpell many think not of, that now we are to have Free Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, and to account no man unclean in the uſe of them.</p>
               <p>My Brethren, there are ſome touches of the Law and Superſtition on you; you know what a ſacred thing was made of the Communion Table when the Rail was about it: now I pray think how you refine and ſpirituallize your old Superſtition, by putting a ſpirituall rayl about the Sacrament, when you debarre poor ſinners from comming hither; Let us take heed, there will be ſomething of the Phariſee in theſe ſpirituall proud hearts of men, there will be ſetting a rail ſtill about the Communion Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble.</p>
               <pb n="80" facs="tcp:109976:44"/>
               <p>Rep. <hi>But are we not faulty and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take of other mens Sins, if we do not our best to have the Leaven purged out, and therefore we may not ſay,</hi> Am I my Brothers keeper, <hi>look they to it?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I Anſwer. There are ſeverall dutyes of a Chriſtian he is to do: He is to pray, receive; He is to love his neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour: Among the reſt there is a duty (much neglected) of brotherly Admonition, whereby we are to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buke the faulty, and to tell the Church of them, ſuppoſing it in a capacity to hear us, if we neglect our duty we are guilty in ſome meaſure, partakers of their ſin, and defiled by it; well, let this be granted; what ther? why we muſt labour a Church eſtabliſhment, and ſo to amend this great neglect among us, but I hope it will not follow, that in the mean while we muſt not receive the Sacrament, pray, nor per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form thoſe other ſeveral duties we have to doe, it is a plain fallacy (<hi>à dicto ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliciter ad dictum ſecundùm quid</hi> I take it) to think our comming to the Sacrament with a wicked man is ſin it ſelf, or makes it the ſin, or us more guilty of the ſin, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:109976:44"/>we ought to have admoniſhed them, and laboured their excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation: no, this neglect of ours is the ſin by it ſelf, and the comming is our duty: God forbid that I ſhould think, if I do ſin in omiting one thing, that I muſt not therefore go to do my duty in another. Becauſe go to do my duty in another. Becauſe the leven is not purged out muſt there be no lumpe? this was, I may hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly ſay, a too overly ſurpriſe of godly Mr. <hi>Burroughs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Rep But you will ſay more ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viouſly. <hi>Are not all ignorant and ſcandalous perſons Swine and Dogs, to be rejected and kept from the Pearls and holy things of the Sacrament?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I anſwer, I dare not ſay ſo; though I ſee what intereſt lies at ſtake, which may ſoon fancy a Chriſtian convenien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, into a Divine neceſſity,</p>
               <p>For Firſt, This is <hi>Petitio Principii,</hi> and if you ſpeak indefinitely, my proofs aſſure the contrary.</p>
               <p>Secondly, I place a great diſtance be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween an unfitnes to come unto the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament as in other duties (<hi>Let a man ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amine himſelf</hi>) and being excluded.</p>
               <pb n="82" facs="tcp:109976:45"/>
               <p>Thirdly, the keeping of any cannot be pretended to, without power in our uneldred Congregations, it being con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed a power not of order, but of juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, men may be Dogs and Swine, either in the courſe of their lives, or in the publick eſteem of the Church; now in our Miniſteriall ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion, we are to look on men as they are in the Churches eſteem; and may not account or deal with them as Dogs (as wee cannot execute an arrant thief) untill they are juridically cenſured to be ſuch, by lawfull authority. And though they have no right here <hi>in foro poli, Det,</hi> yet they have <hi>in foro ſoli, Eccleſiae.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Fifthly, To ſpeak particularly: Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the ignorant, I dare not judge ſo rigorouſly; The 5 <hi>Heb.</hi> 2. comes neer me heart; there are many ſorts of ignorance, the caſe whereof may need inſtruction moſtly, not cenſure; Now that, the very ſolemnity, with all our Preaching, Catechiſme, and exhortati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, doth (I conceive) afford, to all of capacity, (who only come) fully infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming them of the difference between this Sacred Table and common bread; which is diſcerning the Lords body, 1
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:109976:45"/>
                  <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.29. Sufficient happily to our ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion though not to their Salvation. For the ſcandalous we know there muſt be admonition firſt, twice or thrice, <hi>Mat.</hi> 18.15.16. And then if they continue obſtinate (not elſe) and are notorious, an Excommunication is granted. <hi>verſe</hi> 17.1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.13. yet I cannot find any where (unleſs I look without the book) that this is meerly in reference to the Sacrament, but from Chriſtian Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion in generall; at leaſt in the primary nature thereof, though I will yield much by way of indulgence, unto the Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es wiſedome, according to the ancient practiſe of the <hi>Iews</hi> and <hi>Greek</hi> Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans; the ſeverall ſpecies or rather de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees whereof I muſt leave unto more Learned Rabbies, And as to this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent writ of ſuſpenſion in hand, which men would have a middle thing be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween Admonition and Excommunica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, I muſt make my return truly, <hi>Non eſt inventa, in baliva nostra.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I ſpeak it with reverence to wiſer judgments, who may allow as prudent, in the way of Diſcipline, what they will not enforce upon the Conſcience, as ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary, in our worſhip.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="objection">
               <pb n="84" facs="tcp:109976:46"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Obj. 10.</hi> The laſt Objection is from thoſe ſeverall Texts that are alleged for a ſeparation from wicked perſons.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Unto all which I anſwer briefly, and (I conceive with ſubmiſſion) fully; Separation from wicked men is either in regard of their ſinnes; or their Perſons In regard of their ſinnes, it conſiſts in departing from their evill courſes; In regard of their perſons, it is either in caſe of common familiarity, or in caſe of Excommunication. Now it is certaine we muſt ſeparate,
<list>
                     <item>Firſt, from all wicked men in their ſins and evill courſes, this is out of que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion.</item>
                     <item>Secondly, we grant that we muſt ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parate alſo from them in common fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliarity; taking heed of intimacy and keeping them company, leſt we be par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers of their ſin, by infection or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nivance with them.</item>
                     <item>But Thirdly, I affirme there is no Scripture commands our ſeparation from them in the Sacrament, or any of Gods publick Ordinances, unleſs in caſe of Excommunication; which alone can debar any from Church-communion.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <pb n="85" facs="tcp:109976:46"/>
               <p>In the firſt ſenſe you muſt take theſe Scriptures, <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.11 1 <hi>Cor</hi> 10.20.21. Theſe <hi>Corinths</hi> did well to come to the Lords Table, their ſin was only in partaking with Idols. ſo 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.14. to the end, where they are rebuk'd for joyning in the ſame ſin of Idolatry. If you underſtand this, <hi>Be not unequally yokt,</hi> of Marriage, compare it with 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.13.14. There the beleeving wife muſt in no wiſe ſeperate from her Infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dell husband, here ſhe muſt come out &amp; be ſeperate, how can this be reconci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led but that ſhe may have communion with the Perſon in what is Lawfull, and yet be ſeperate from him in his ways, that are evill? You may adde happily in this firſt ſenſe. <hi>Ier.</hi> 15.19.2. <hi>Theſ.</hi> 3.6.11. <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.6. All which texts are hereby an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, that though indeed they doe command a ſeparation from the wicked; it is from them in their ſinnes, not from joyning with them in doing our duty.</p>
               <p>In the ſecond ſenſe, you may take 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.9. to the 12.2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 3.14. <hi>Rom.</hi> 16.17.2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.5.2 <hi>Io.</hi> 10.11. <hi>Pro.</hi> 22.24.25. and it may be 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 3.6. <hi>Tit.</hi> 3 10 and ſo theſe Scriptures are like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe anſwered, which doe further for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid us the wickeds familiarity, as their
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:109976:47"/>ſins; not a bare accompanying with any in Gods Ordinances.</p>
               <p>Rep. But you wil ſay, <hi>If I muſt decline a wicked man, ſo as not to eat with him,</hi> (which I interpret by our ordinary converſatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) <hi>how much more muſt I decline him at this Sacrament?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I anſwer, this is a clear fallacy, I am ſorry to ſee many graveld in their minds at it; as if there were any force in this, I muſt not be ſuch a mans com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon companion, therefore I muſt not goe to Church with him: wee muſt know, Arguments from the leſſe to the greater, muſt be in things of the ſame kind and nature; Now it is one thing to eat at home, an indifferent action where I am left to my own arbitration and muſt not chuſe evill, I mean in pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferring bad ſociety: and another to eat at the Sacrament, which I am bound unto as a piece of the ſervice of God, &amp; cannot omit at my pleaſure, without of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fending his command. Let me adde (to explain, and avoid ſcruple) I may ſin in admitting one into my friendſhip, whom nevertheleſſe I may lawfully be
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:109976:47"/>withall I doubt not, (and at Table too) on my occaſions.</p>
               <p>In the third ſenſe I take <hi>Mat.</hi> 18.17. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.1. to the 9. where the whole Communion or Life of Chriſtians, is compared to an unleavened Feaſt (from which that Perſon was to be excluded in generall) without peculiar mention (as ſome would have it) of the Sacrament; you may reckon hither many places <hi>Io.</hi> 9.22. 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.20, &amp;c. In which caſe only when excommunicated, the matter is granted. And thus I am apt to think, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.9.10.11. 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 3.6.14. 2 <hi>Io.</hi> 10. &amp;c. quoted in the ſecond ſenſe before, if ſtrictly taken, ſtands in full force only. As for <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.6. which properly concerns Admonition. <hi>Ier.</hi> 15, 19.1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.22. which, (with ſome cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monious precepts of the Law as 2 <hi>Chron<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> 23.19.) In the words, are much applyed for the ſcaring of many Conſciences, I muſt appeal to other Iudgments when they are well weighed, whether in their proper ſenſe and importance they are not many leagues off this peculiar buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the Sacrament.</p>
               <p>I will conclude with 4 Wiſhes:
<list>
                     <item>1. I Wiſh wee had a Government e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſht in the Church, the neereſt in Chriſtian prudence that may be, to the word of God:</item>
                     <pb n="88" facs="tcp:109976:48"/>
                     <item>2. I Wiſh the duty of Fraternall correption, a watching over, and admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhing one another in love were better known and practiſed amongſt us.</item>
                     <item>3. I Wiſh that men would look more into their own conſciences, and leave the judging of others ſpirits, hearts, and reines alone, to the judgment ſeat of Chriſt.</item>
                     <item>4. I Wiſh, though there may be ſome judging by the fruits, that wiſe religious men would be more cautious of counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nancing theſe ſeparations in the viſible Church, ſeeing upon the ſame ground that you goe to gather a Church out of my mixt Congregation, another will ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther a ſeparation our of your Church; and ſo continue (as I have intimated fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our ſad experience) an endleſſe ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rating, untill this firſt ſeparation ſhall in a few years be able to take up the ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of that Greateſt Grandmother, unto thoſe many ſchiſms ſhe ſhall ſee iſſuing, as her naturall offſpring, out of her own bowels, Riſe up Daughter, goe to thy Daughter, for thy Daughters Daughter has a Daughter; for this ſeparations ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration has a ſeparation.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <closer>Deo Gloria, mihi Condonatio;</closer>
               <closer>
                  <signed>J. H.</signed>
               </closer>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <pb facs="tcp:109976:48"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
